Guide to the Josephine Procopio Albarelli Collection of Gilberto Owen and Elías Nandino
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Josephine Procopio Albarelli collection of Gilberto Owen and Elías Nandino
1948-2000
GEN MSS 1132
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.54
(5 boxes) + 1 record album storage, 1 roll, 2 art
Procopio, Josefina
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
4 (Record album storage) (sound recordings): Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Josephine Procopio Albarelli, 2001-2004.
Scope and Contents
The Josephine Procopio Albarelli Collection of Gilberto Owen and Elías Nandino contains correspondence, mostly letters to Albarelli from Owen, 1948-1951, and from Nandino, 1951-1989; autograph manuscript and typescript poems and other writings by Owen and Nandino, copies of their writings made by Albarelli, and proofs for her editions of Owen's Poesía y prosa and Obras, 1950s-1980s; sound recordings, including readings of poetry by Nandino and Alí Chumacero (Voz viva de México; Serie literatura mexicana, 1960s); photographs and negatives of Owen, Nandino, Albarelli, and others, undated; two oil paintings by Nandino, undated; drawings by Hector Xavier for illustrations of books by Nandino, 1950s; and related clippings, posters, and other printed material. Some materials are accompanied by identifying notes written by Albarelli. Research strengths include Mexican literature, 1950s-1990s, especially poetry of Owen and Nandino and their association with Los Contemporáneos; and Albarelli's editing of writings by Owen.
Elías Nandino (1900-1993)
Elías Nandino (1900-1993), Mexican poet. Nandino was associated with Los Contemporáneos, a modernist literary movement in Mexico, 1920s-1930s.
Gilberto Owen (1904-1952)
Gilberto Owen (1904-1952), Mexican poet, journalist, and diplomat. Owen was associated with Los Contemporáneos, a modernist literary movement in Mexico, 1920s-1930s. He worked as a journalist for El Tiempo, Bogota, Colombia, during the 1930s, served as a diplomat in the United States, Peru, and Ecuador, 1928-1942, and was Mexican vice consul in Philadelphia during the 1940s.
Josephine Procopio Albarelli
Josephine Procopio Albarelli; also used the name Josefina Procopio; editor of Gilberto Owen's Poesía y prosa (México: Imprenta Universitaria, 1953) and Obras (México: Fondo de cultura económica, 1979).
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Papers Relating to Gilberto Owen, 1948-1997. II. Papers Relating to Elías Nandino, 1950-2000.
Authors, Mexican -- 20th Century -- Archives; Editors -- Mexico; Mexican poetry -- 20th Century; Mexican literature -- 20th Century; Modernism (Literature) -- Mexico; Poets, Mexican -- 20th Century -- Archives; Audiovisual materials -- Mexico -- 20th Century; Drawings (visual works) -- Mexico -- 20th Century; Long-playing records -- Mexico -- 20th Century; Photographs -- Mexico -- 20th Century; Photographs -- United States -- 20th Century; Authors -- Mexico -- 20th Century; Editors -- Mexico -- 20th Century; Editors -- United States -- 20th Century; Poets -- Mexico -- 20th Century; Chumacero, Alí, 1918-2010; Nandino, Elías, 1900-1993; Owen, Gilberto, 1904-1952; Procopio, Josefina; Villaurrutia, Xavier, 1903-1950; Xavier, Hector
- Papers Relating to Gilberto Owen, 1948-1997, undated; Series I; 1.04; (3 boxes) + 1 record album storage
  Arrangement
  Organized into four subseries: Correspondence, Writings, Other Papers, and Sound Recordings
  - Correspondence
    Scope and Contents
    Letters are to Albarelli, unless otherwise noted. Some letters are accompanied by poems or photographs
    - Fondo de cultura económica, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Owen, Gilberto, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Owen, Gilberto, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Owen, Gilberto, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Owen, Gilberto, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Owen, Gilberto (to Elías Nandino, with poems), 1952, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Owen, Gilberto (to Salvador Novo and Rafael Heliodoro Valle), 1949 August (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Owen, Gilberto (to "Connie," a sister of Albarelli), undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Reyes, Alfonso (to Owen), 1948 July 20 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Staiger, Ralph C. With "Gilberto Owen: A Remembrance" (typescript photocopy), 1979-1981, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Unsorted, 1952-1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Writings
    - Bibliography of works by Owen (notes by Albarelli), undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Cabell, James Branch. The Witch-Woman: A Trilogy About Her (Spanish translation by Owen). Notes, typescript, revised, and photocopy, circa 1952-1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      With related article by José Rojas Garcidueñas
    - "De la ardua lección" (poem, on the death of Xavier Villaurrutia). Drafts, autograph manuscript and typescripts, with revisions, circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - "Defensa del hombre" and "Examen de pausas" (poems). "Copies made from 1953 edition," manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - "Desvelo" and "Línea" (poems). Copies made by Albarelli, typescript, with annotations by Owen, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Obras (Fondo de cultura económica, 1979). Page proofs, photocopies, with revisions, circa 1979 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Poems. Manuscript and typescript copies, signed, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Poems and other writings (copies made by Albarelli). Typescript, with autograph manuscript annotations by Owen, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Poems and other writings in La gaceta, número 90 and número 100. Printed, 1978, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Poems and other writings in Prometus, número 3. Printed, 1952 May (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Poesía y prosa (México: Fondo de cultura económica, 1978). Page proof, circa 1978 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Poesía y prosa (publication contract between Albarelli and the Universidad nacional autónoma de México). Typescript carbon, signed, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 2, Folder 24-26)
  - Other Papers
    - Articles about Owen in Letras de sinaloa: tribuna de la juventud, número 41. Printed, 1954 February 14 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Clippings about Owen, 1952-1997, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Concert programs for the Philadelpha Orchestra, 1951-1952 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Notes by Albarelli, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Photographs of Owen, Albarelli, and others, undated (Box 3, Folder 31-33)
    - Photographs of Owen, Albarelli, and others (negatives), undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Photographs of Albarelli's apartment, Philadelphia, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Sound Recordings
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
    - Chumacero, Ali. Poemas (selección): voce del autor (Voz viva de México). Serie literatura mexicana, 1964; 1 12" sound disc (Box 4 (Record album storage), Folder 36)
    - Owen, Gilberto. Poemas (selección): voces de Claudio Obregon y Oscar Chavez (Voz viva de México). Serie literatura mexicana, 1965; 1 12" sound disc (Box 4 (Record album storage), Folder 37)
    - Thompson, Virgil. Four Saints in Three Acts ( RCA Victor Red Seal Records, DM 1244), undated; 5 12" sound discs (Box 4 (Record album storage), Folder 38)
    - Walton, William. Facade. Edith Sitwell, reader (Columbia Masterworks, MM 829), copyright 1949; 4 12" sound discs (Box 4 (Record album storage), Folder 39)
- Papers Relating to Elías Nandino, 1950-2000, undated; Series II; 0.5; (2 boxes) + 1 roll, 2 art
  Organized into three subseries: Correspondence, Writings, and Other Papers
  - Correspondence
    - Nandino, Elías, 1951-1952 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Nandino, Elías, 1957-1962 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Nandino, Elías (to Josephine Procopio Albarelli and Alfonso Albarelli), 1971-1976 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Nandino, Elías (to Josephine Procopio Albarelli and Alfonso Albarelli), 1977-1982 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Nandino, Elías, 1987-1989 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Mendoza-López, Margarita, 1983 July (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Rojas Garcidueñas, José, 1979 October 6 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Soriano, Juan (with drawings), 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Unsorted, 1989, undated (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Writings
    - Cerca de lo lejos: poesía, 1972-1978 (México: Fondo de Cultura Económica, 1979). Typescript, with printed copy, 1977-1987 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - "Circulo eterno" (poem). Typescript carbon, with manuscript revisions, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - "Decimas a Xavier Villaurrutia" (poems). Typescript, 1950 December 25 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Sonnets "XV," "XVI," and "XVII". Typescript, with manuscript revisions, undated (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Other Papers
    - Clippings about Elías Nandino, 1995-2000 (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - Notes by Albarelli about paintings by Nandino, undated (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Photographs of Nandino and Albarelli, undated (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Printed material, 1956-2000, undated (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Xavier, Hector. Illustrations for Nandino, Elías, Naufragio de la duda (México: Nueva Voz, 1950). 1 drawing, circa 1950 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 57)
    - Xavier, Hector. Illustrations for Nandino, Elías, Triángulo de silencios (México: Editorial Guaranía, 1953). 5 drawings, circa 1953 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 58-62)
    - Posters about Nandino, Gilberto Owen, and Roberto Montenegro, 1978, undated (Box 7 (Roll))
    - Nandino, Elías. Unidentified (oil painting), undated; 1 framed painting (Box 8 (Art))
    - Nandino, Elías. Unidentified (oil painting), undated; 1 framed painting (Box 9 (Art))